Pete Welding collection, 1958-1995
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 8: Sound recordings
  - Subseries 4: Compilations of dubbed commercial recordings
    - Anthology of Boogie KERA FM, 1976, AFC 2011/053: SR455; RXH 4695; 1 sound tape reel (Side A, part 1: 01:51:44; Side 1, part 2: 00:12:37, Side 2, part 1: 01:51:59, Side 2, part 2: 00:16:18): analog, 3 3/4 ips, stereo; 7 in.
      00:12:14 CC talks about Erskine Butterfield, pianist, was from Syracuse New York. He hit it up with various groups in very early of 40s and faded from playing the boogie woogie after WW2. He died in New York in 1961, but left an interesting legacy of boogie woogie, featuring his piano work, and many vocals. His style, like Count Basie, is relaxed and easy-going. In going over his list of recordings, it almost seemed as if he is obsessed with food, starting with his own name (Butterfield) to his more outstanding recordings he called "Salt Butter," "Chocolate," and "Blackberry Jam." Let's hear this last one in 1941, Erskine and His Blue Boys, playing "Blackberry Jam."
      00:13:23 "Blackberry Jam"
      00:16:37 CC talks: There is Mary Lou Williams again sitting at her piano. Last time she played with Andy Kirk. This time she is accompanying singer, Mildred Bailey, as a rhythm group called Mildred Bailey and Her Oxford Greys. Here is a good example of a song done in a boogie woogie van, where the vocalist is dominant, Mary Lou William's piano mainly serves as a backup. Mildred Bailey is telling us a dim lighted tavern in Birmingham, where laughing water coming out from a strange fountain. She calls this "Barrel House Music"
      00:17:13 "Barrel House Music"
      00:20:13 CC talks: Wingy Manone, trumpeter and vocalist, was another jazz artist and showman. When he lost his arm in a street car accident in New Orleans when he was only 8 years old, back in 1922, learned to play the trumpet with his left hand. In his 30s and 40s, he was a prolific recording artist, recording with people like Teddy Wilson, Jelly Roll Morton, Artie Shaw, Bob Crosby and others. 1941, Wingy finally decided he better capture the growing boogie woogie market and recorded "The Boogie Beat'll Getcha."
      00:21:27 "The Boogie Beat'll Getcha"
      00:24:45 CC talks: One of my favorite pieces is Harry James's fast pace boogie woogie he did in 1939. Albert Ammons was doing the piano work. What an interesting interplay of early blue playing of James, and piano virtuosity of Ammons. A tremendous combination. And this is called "Woo-Woo."
      00:25:09 "Woo-Woo"
      00:28:23 Charlie the Collector ends the show.
      00:29:40 An unidentified person announces there are more talks about Big Band Boogie-Woogie Anthology.
      00:30:07 The start of another episode of talk with Charlie the Collector on boogie woogie.
      00:30:52 CC talks: This is program #6 in the series on boogie woogie. After 1942, boogie woogie started its decline, primarily due to the overexposure and devastation of WW2. However its demise was not sudden nor complete, it was just begin to fade and change nature. There were still many excellent boogie woogie performances into the 60s primarily by the old-timers who managed to survive that long. This time we are going to explore piano boogie woogie made after 1942, by some of the more famous pianists, some of whom have been around since the 20s. First on our list is a 256-pound pianist, Big Maceo Merriweather, whose recording career was all too short. His most outstanding recording is probably the one in 1945: "Chicago Breakdown." The piece was praised by a jazz critic as one of the best boogie woogie piano solos in the complete history of jazz.
      00:32:38 "Chicago Breakdown" played by Big Maceo Merriweather
      00:35:35 CC talks: Little Brother Montgomery, a blue singer and pianist from Louisiana, persisted in playing the original form of the blues. Not primarily a player of boogie woogie, but he did do it and the results are excellent and original. Here is an example of his uniquely idea of the boogie woogie, a recording he did with drummer Frank "Sweet" Williams, in 1951, called "Shreveport Farewell."
      00:36:18 "Shreveport Farewell" played by Little Brother Montgomery and Frank "Sweet" Williams.
      00:39:01 CC talks: In the mid 40s, a young pianist, Harry "The Hipster" Gibson, used to play in various clubs in New York on 52nd street. Praised by jazz critics in 1944 as a jazz sensation, he quickly faded in obscurity by 1957. He was talented and left a legacy of piano virtuosity. Let's hear this piece recorded on the Musicraft label in 1944, which presents some good right hand work: "Barrelhouse Boogie" with John Simmons (bass) and Sid Catlett (drums).
      00:39:57 "Barrelhouse Boogie" played by Harry "The Hipster" Gibson with John Simmons (bass) and Sid Catlett (drums).
      00:43:00 CC talks: One of the most outstanding piano boogie woogie piano number is a piece recorded by Cow Davenport in 1927, which rises with "Pinetop's Boogie Woogie" recorded a year later but never received the wide spread fame. Davenport called it "Cow Cow Blues," but not to be confused with Cow Cow Boogie Woogie. The best rendition of Cow Cow Blues is the one played in 1961 by "Memphis Slim" Peter Chapman who is the most authentic blue artist of his generation. Since this piece was recorded in 1961, it was done with new hi-fi technology.
      00:44:28 Memphis Slim Peter Chatman dedicated his playing of "Cow Cow Blues" to Cow Cow Davenport.
      00:48:16 CC talks: Now a boogie woogie in the low register. The recording is done by "Cripple" Clarence Lofton in 1943. Lofton is another old-timer, born in Tennessee in 1896, recorded on the old Paramount labels as early as 1930, died in 1956. He spent his productive years in Chicago and his unusual style influence many young pianists. He called this one "Southend Boogie," an obvious reference to the fact that his left hand was about as far left as he could get on the 88 keyboard.
      00:49:03 "Southend Boogie" by "Cripple" Clarence Lofton
      00:52:20 CC talks: Russia also made a valuable contribution to the American jazz world. pianist Art Hodes, whose family moved to Chicago in 1905. Hodes was always a crusader for traditional jazz, and played a simple blues style. His style was highly influenced by Jelly Roll Morton and James Pete Johnson. Here is a recording he did with bass player Truck Parham: "Pinetop's Blues" which was originally played and recorded by Pinetop Smith in 1928. Hodes' version of "Pinetop's Blues" has a duo advantage and more advanced piano technique.
      00:53:13 "Pinetop's Blues" played by Art Hodes and Truck Parham
      00:56:41 CC talks about Hodes' definition about boogie woogie and ends the show.
      00:58:40 An unidentified man made a closing remark about Charlie the Collectors' passion about boogie woogie and his show.
      00:59:51 An unidentified man makes an opening remark about Charlie the Collector's show: Boogie-Woogie anthology program #7.
      01:01:02 Pre-show music plays.
      01:03:26 CC talks: We will listen to big band boogie in this episode-Teddy Powell and his orchestra plays Teddy's Boogie Woogie in 1939.
      01:03:53 Teddy's Boogie Woogie played by Teddy Powell and his orchestra.
      01:07:12 CC talks: Teddy's Boogie Woogie is one of Teddy Powell's 7 big band boogie pieces from 1939 to 1941, which was followed by Teddy Bear Boogie, Boogin' On The Downbeat, Bluebird Boogie-Woogie, Straight Eight Boogie, Jungle Boogie and In Pinetop's Footsteps. The CC talks about Woody Herman, clarinetist and a band leader, who made it big and stayed with all the trends of jazz music. They were known as The Band that Plays the Blues. One of the popular songs of 1940, was this hybrid rhythm of rhumba and boogie woogie, called "Simply Rhumboogie."
      01:08:34 "Simply Rhumboogie" performed by Woody Herman and his band, pianist Tommy Linehan, and vocalist Dillagene.
      01:11:59 CC talks: Meade "Lux" Lewis wrote and recorded a boogie woogie piece to honor his mentor Jimmy Yancey in 1936, called "Yancey Special." On March 10, 1938, Bob Crosby and his big band recorded this piece featuring Bob Zurke displaying his immense skills on the piano. Interestingly it was arranged by Dean Kincaide, who also did Tommy Dorsey's boogie woogie.
      01:12:48 "Yancey Special" performed by Bob Crosby and his orchestra with Bob Zurke on the piano.
      01:16:19 CC talks: Bob Zurke, left the Crosby band to form his own group called the Delta Rhythm Band. Like many of the leaders of the band, Zurke also capitalize on the fame of boogie woogie. Using his own piano talents but somehow it just didn't go over commercially. Bob Zurke did an arrangement of "Cow Cow Blues" in 1940 for the big band.
      01:17:24 "Cow Cow Blues" by Bob Zurke and his Delta Rhythm Band.
      01:20:16 CC talks: Johnny Long, a left-handed violinist, never featured himself in any recordings. He only recorded one boogie woogie and it was a good one. He most famous recording is "A Shanty In Old Shanty Town" in 1940. Just like many band leaders in the 30s and 40s, Johnny felt compelled to make recordings of boogie woogie, "The Boogie Man."
      01:21:04 "Boogie Man" by Johnny Long featuring Paul Harmon on vocal.
      01:24:17 CC talks: We don't usually associate Bing Crosby with boogie woogie, but he did make a good one. Bing Crosby and Lionel Hampton did a version of "Pinetop's Boogie Woogie" in 1947. In several recordings Crosby talks rather than sings, and Hampton is in grand style with his two-finger approach in his keyboard style.
      01:25:00 "Pinetop's Boogie Woogie" by Bing Crosby and Lionel Hampton.
      01:28:28 CC made a closing remark about the program.
      01:29:40 An unidentified man made a closing remark about Charlie the Collector's show.
      01:31:10 The above episode ends abruptly. A new episode of the boogie woogie anthology show starts. Charlie the Collector talks about variations of boogie woogie, such as how boogie woogie blended with other musical forms, and how it was handled by instruments other than piano. Will Bradley in the late 40s made a boogie woogie recording called "Bob and Boogie," Garland [Bartol] put it to a cha cha, and there is Rhumboogie. And Will Bradley also did a boogie woogie conga, Joe "Fingers" Carr did a waltz boogie, [Hosea Turby] with his boogie woogie etudes, and Spike Johns once got into the act.
      01:33:37 "The Yellow Dog Blues" by Eddie Condon and his Orchestra featuring pianist Ralph Sutton
      01:36:25 CC talks: This is a boogie woogie performance based on the human voice, a vocal quartet that form the regular figuration of the bass and right hand melody normally associated with piano. The song is "Gospel Boogie," in 1940s, on an off-brand label called the White Church, performed by Leroy Abernathy of the Homeland Harmony Quartet. The beautiful walking bass is performed by the human voice, generating the 8-bar gospel message.
      01:37:15 "Gospel Boogie" by Leroy Abernathy of the Homeland Harmony Quartet.
      01:40:17 CC talks: Boogie woogie also has its contemporary and modern aspects. Mary Lou Williams 1947 did a smooth and polished performance reflecting her tremendous harmonic sense, "Hesitation Boogie," an example of an invasion of an early contemporary jazz to the realm of boogie woogie.
      01:40:50 "Hesitation Boogie" performed by Mary Lou Williams
      01:43:33 CC talks: Here is a single instrument doing the boogie woogie. In the 50s, the evolution of tape recording allows artists to accompany themselves, by successfully record themselves and by playing back indefinite times. Jack Marshall done probably in the mid-50s a piece solely of his guitar, playing in different registers doing of the bass figuration, as well as the breaks and the melodic lines. It's called "Tremolo Boogie." You will also recognize that it is the arrangement of the original Pinetops.
      01:44:49 "Tremolo Boogie" by Jack Marshall.
      01:47:11 CC talks: Country and Western music also sees boogie woogie as a suitable theme, they are a little late in the game and some of the results are monstrous. But these two forms are certainly not incompatible. Most incompatibility probably comes from lack of proper instrumentation, notably a piano. Here is a piece in 1940 done by a group called The Village Boys, a Western swing band of piano and strings in the Houston area. This piece is called "A Boogie Woogie in the Village." It is an example of boogie woogie in the country and western van, or, is it western and country in the boogie woogie van?
      01:48:15 "Boogie Woogie in the Village" by The Village Boys.
      01:51:03 CC talks: Milt Herth was a pioneer of the Hammond electric organ, popular in the late 30s. He recorded with the Milt Herth Trio, which usually included the piano and drums, in addition to his Hammond organ. Before he died in 1969, he left us a shining example of how boogie woogie could be handled on an electric organ, with the aids of the piano keyboard on some of the right-hand boogie riffs. Here is a piece recorded in 1947. Euday Bowman would be proud that "12th Street Rag" would be played in such a grand style.
      01:51:44 End
      Side 1, Part 2
      Start "12th Street Rag" played by Milt Herth and the Milt Herth Trio
      00:03:23 CC talks: Rock and roll found some of its roots in boogie woogie. Rock and roll artists like Piano Red, Jerry Lee Lewis and Amos Milburn framed their early music into boogie woogie format. Here is Amos Milburn in 1949, doing an early rock and roll version of the original "Pinetop's Boogie Woogie."
      00:04:08 "Pinetop's Boogie Woogie" played by Amos Milburn
      00:07:00 CC made a closing remark of the show.
      00:09:08 Unidentified music plays.
      00:12:37 End
      Side 2, Part 1
      Start CC talks about overview of boogie woogie.
      00:03:43 "Pinetop's Boogie Woogie" performed by Pinetop Smith
      00:07:06 CC talks: One of the pioneers of boogie woogie was Jimmy Blythe, an early Chicago pianist, He made several recordings in the mid-20s with some of the famous musicians such as clarinetists Johnny Dodds. The first boogie woogie was probably done by Jimmy Blythe in 1924, a piano solo called "Chicago Stop." Here is piano duet he made with Jim "Buddy" Burton in April 1928, about six months before Pinetop Smith recorded his milestone. This is an example of an early boogie woogie style before it even acquired its name. They called this "Block and Tackle," referring a type of moonshine, selling for $25 a half pint that would make you walk a block down the street to tackle any kinds of automobile.
      00:08:28 "Block and Tackle" played by Jimmy Blythe and Johnny Dodds.
      00:11:03 CC talks: Let's hear a piece of a sample in the 40s of what I call the boogie woogie era. The big three successful pianists Pete Johnson, Albert Ammons, and Meade Lux Lewis. Here is a piece duet of Johnson and Ammons, which also includes a drum accompaniment, constituting boogie with another related but different piano style, called barrelhouse.
      00:12:12 "Barrelhouse Boogie" by Pete Johnson and Albert Ammons.
      00:15:17 CC talks: In the late 30s, many big bands adapted to perform boogie woogie. Here is an example of the best big band boogie woogie. Red Nichols leads several of his bands, recorded with pianist Billy Maxted doing some fast finger work in 1940. This piece is called "Meet Miss 8 Beat."
      00:16:46 "Meet Miss 8 Beat" performed by Red Nichols and Billy Maxted
      00:19:30 CC talks: Small groups play boogie woogie and they are jazzy, exciting and like chamber music, or like bar room music. Sam Price, from Honey Grove Texas, used to lead a small group that he called Texas Bluesicians. During the 1940s they made a bunch of records for Decca. Their music is primarily in the blues format dominated by Price's piano. Here is what they sound in 1940, co-composed by Sam Price, called "How 'Bout That Mess."
      00:20:35 "How 'Bout That Mess" by Sam Price
      00:23:31 CC talks: Boogie woogie finds its way into other format of musical expression. That's exactly what happens when boogie woogie reached its heyday in the 40s. Let's hear it how it influenced the early rock and roll music. Here is "Swanee River Hop" by Fats Domino in 1953.
      00:24:30 "Swanee River Hop" by Fats Domino
      00:27:18 CC made a closing remark on the boogie woogie program.
      00:28:54 The start of another boogie woogie program. Charlie the Collector (CC) talks about the early pioneers of boogie woogie. First on the list is Romeo Nelson. Very little is known about this man. He lived in Chicago and only did a few records. "Head Rag Hop" was probably his best recording, made in September 1929. The influence of the Pinetops is obvious in the talking and dancing instructions.
      00:30:52 "Head Rag Hop" by Romeo Nelson
      00:33:48 CC talks: Boogie woogie seemed to evolve during the early 20s, blending the early ragtime and the blues piano. It is a form that retains both the basic blues played bu the right hand and resounding excitement of ragtime, usually doubled in tempo played by the left hand. One of the most interesting of this blending on 1927 recording made by James P. Johnson called "All That I Had is Gone."
      00:35:33 "All That I Had is Gone" by James P. Johnson.
      00:38:21 CC talks: One of the early boogie woogie artist who disappeared in the 20s, and did not surface again until rediscovery in the late 40s was pianist Charlie Spand, who was also known as a fine blues singer. In 1929 he made a Paramount record with guitarist Blind Blake, called "Hasting Street," on which there is a rhythmic background, and distinguishable xylophone, rattles, and tom toms. Throughout the records, there is a dark, ominous quality, not usually not associated the quality of boogie woogie. Blind Blake is doing the talking.
      00:40:14 "Hasting Street" by Charlie Spand and Blind Blake
      00:43:29 CC talks: Hersal Thomas, another one of the early boogie woogie and blues artist, was sort of a child prodigy at the piano. His most famous composition, "Suitcase Blues," which he recorded in February 1925, was commented by some critics to be the first boogie woogie ever made. Now we know Jimmy Blythe beat him by ten months with his "Chicago Stomp." But "Suitcase Blues" was a milestone in the art, because it was played and remembered by many other boogie woogie players.
      00:44:35 "Suitcase Blues" by Hersal Thomas
      00:47:12 CC talks: The Pinetops' boogie woogie was made in 1928 in which the jazz style was given its name. The most significant milestone in the history of boogie woogie was probably a 1927 recording made by Meade Lux Lewis called "Honky Tonk Train." Lux was born in Chicago in 1905, started to learn violin when he was 16. After hearing Jimmy Yancey's playing he switched to blues piano. In 1927 he recorded for the old Paramount label, one of the most phenomenal boogie woogie piano solos of all time and one that sent jazz promoter John Hammond on a two-year search for the composer.
      00:49:34 "Honky Tonk Train Blues" by Meade Lux Lewis
      00:52:47 CC talks: Boogie woogie basses are quite varied and infinite in numbers. Many artists took pride in inventing new ones. By far the most popular is the simple walking bass, an eight-to-the-bar figuration in which the name implies. Another bass also popular in boogie woogie, called the rocks, it sort of conveys the feeling of back and forth. We are going to listen to a rock bass performed by Montana Taylor. In 1929, he made a recording called "Detroit Rocks" featuring the unique rocking bass figuration.
      00:53:58 "Detroit Rocks" by Montana Taylor
      00:57:18 CC made a closing remark of the show.
      00:58:35 The start of new episode of the boogie woogie program on the radio. Charlie the Collector talks about the boogie woogie era, 1936-1942. The really big three were Albert Ammons, Pete Johnson and Meade Lux Lewis, left us a truly fine legacy, and many recordings of duets and trios. Pete Johnson got his start in Kansas City, playing solo piano in clubs in 1926-1938 until he started to get national exposure. Here is an example of Pete Johnson did in 1941 for Decca, called "Pete's Mixture."
      00:59:56 "Pete's Mixture" by Pete Johnson
      01:02:47 CC talks: Albert Ammons, who does our theme song "Shout For Joy," was a Chicago man. Here is an example of his style, a dynamic recording he did for Blue Note in 1942, he called this "Bass Going Crazy." And it is a departure from the normal boogie woogie pattern. In it the left hand does not allow to pursue the repeating pattern for very long, and develop with melodic pattern usually associated with the right hand.
      01:03:31 "Bass Going Crazy" by Albert Ammons
      01:07:12 CC talks: Mead Lux Lewis's "Honky Tonk Train" was first discovered by John Hammond after a two year search. Lux rose to the height after his discovery and continued to adapt boogie woogie to the trend of the changing taste. Let's listen to his performance in 1936 on "Mr. Freddie Blues," a piece written by Freddie Shayne.
      01:07:42 "Mr. Freddie Blues" performed by Mead Lux Lewis
      01:10:42 CC talks: Let's hear how Lewis sounded in 1962, advancing with the trend of the day, he recorded this moving honky tonk piano piece, with the mashed potato beat building on all his boogie woogie expertise he accumulated since the mid-20s. Let's call it "When The Saints Go Shufflin' In."
      01:11:10 "When The Saints Go Shufflin' In" by Meade Lux Lewis
      01:13:35 CC talks: Jimmy Yancey left a legacy of recordings of outstanding blues style and variety of basses he invented in his lifetime. Here is a recording he did in 1940, "Old Quaker Blues."
      01:15:08 "Old Quaker Blues" by Jimmy Yancey
      01:17:51 CC talks: Let's turn to Kansas City and see what they have to offer. Besides Pete Johnson who was born and trained there as a boogie woogie pianist, Kansas City also produced other boogie woogie pianists like Mary Lou Williams, Count Basie, Joshua Johnson and a band leader by the name of Jay McShann who got his fame because Charlie Parker got started playing in his band in the late 30s. McShann, whose nickname is Hootie, was an accomplished musician, specialized in blues and boogie woogie. Here is something that he did in 1941, called "Hold 'Em Hootie."
      01:19:12 "Hold 'Em Hootie" by Jay McShann
      01:21:50 CC talks: The best piano player of the Boogie Woogie era is Maurice Rocco, was another child prodigy, invented a style called rocking rhythm. He was a jazz artist of the highest caliber. Let's hear his "Donkey Serenade" he did in 1940 when he was only 16. Near the end of piece, he performed another neat trick unique to boogie woogie by switching the melody of the right hand and incorporated into the walking bass.
      01:23:25 "Donkey Serenade" by Maurice Rocco
      01:25:56 CC made a closing remark of the show.
      01:27:00 The start of another episode of Boogie Anthology in which Charlie the Collector is the host. CC talks: We will listen to big band boogie woogie and hear how big group capitalizing this captivating musical style that swept the country in the late 30s and early 40s. Let's start out by listening to Harry James' "Back Beat Boogie."
      01:28:26 "Back Beat Boogie" by Harry James
      01:13:12 CC talks: A more challenging way for the big band to adapt to the piano-dominated nature of boogie woogie, is to let other instruments play the boogie bass figuration, usually the wind instruments. A notable example of the big band boogie is the arrangement of the original Pinetop's boogie woogie made by Tommy Dorsey in 1938, simply under the name "Boogie Woogie."
      01:33:12 "Boogie Woogie" by Tommy Dorsey